This lecture will cover challenges computer architects have in measuring and comparing performance of processors.
Comparing performance can be somewhat complex because there are a lot of factors that come into play.
Let's take a look at four airplanes as a starting point.
If you had to guess which had the best performance, how would you start?
Let's look at the columns.
The 747 clearly can carry the most amount of passengers while the Douglas has the best range.
And finally, the Concorde flew the fastest.
It turns out we can't just look at one metric as all aspects are important to the performance of an airplane.
Ultimately, we need to agree upon some way to rate each aspect into the overall picture.
So let's get back to processors.
How do we decide which metrics are the most important?
If you're a research scientist trying to simulate complex real-world systems, you probably care the most about floating-point performance.
However, if you're a mobile app developer, you're going to be compiling a lot of code,
and integer performance will be key to minimize recompilation time.
Finally, if I'm deploying a cloud service that uses very large databases sharded across many physical machines,
I'm going to want very good memory as well as IO latency and bandwidth.
Ultimately, if you're buying a computer and you want the fastest, you need to know about the workloads you care about.
And when you're architecting a new processor, you can't run these workloads and measure them.
So we need to be able to project performance just based on the organization and features.
One high-order bit is cost.
If you don't care about cost, you'll be able to design the fastest processor limited only by physics and processed technology.
But in the real world, where you need to be able to sell your processors for a profit, performance per price is going to be crucial to be a success.
In the remaining time, we're going to cover the following four topics.
First, we'll cover important metrics of computer performance, including latency and throughput, how to average these metrics, as well as the iron law and Omdahl's law.
To define performance, we must consider what is important to whom.
What's important to a normal person using their laptop or mobile device?
Perhaps they care about the time it takes for a program to run.
This response time is simply the time difference between the end time and the start time, and we call that response time or latency.
However, from the perspective of a computer center or super competing center manager, it's advantageous to maximize the rate of jobs that are successfully being completed.
This metric is called throughput.
You've probably dealt with these metrics before in your daily lives.
When playing an online game, your ping time or latency is important so you don't lag.
If you're downloading a software update, the bandwidth or data throughput is what you notice the most.
So how are these metrics related?
Is the throughput of a system always inversely proportional to the response time of a program?
It turns out they're inversely proportional only if there's no overlap between the jobs being run.
If there's any overlap, then the throughput will be greater than one over the average response time.
Let's consider a lunch buffet with five entrees, and for illustration, let's assume it takes everyone two minutes to dish up that entree to their plate.
This puts the total fill rate of five entrees times two minutes each, equal to ten minutes.
The throughput, however, is not one plate every ten minutes.
When plate one dishes up the red entree, they move to the blue entree.
The person behind them, with plate two, can immediately start dishing up the red entree.
This effectively forms what we will call a pipeline as shown in the diagram before.
So while each plate takes ten minutes to fill with five entrees,
once the buffet line is filled with five people dishing up simultaneously,
you can see that we're filling five plates in ten minutes, so our throughput is one plate completion every two minutes.
As an architect, what can we do to improve performance?
Well, we could simply build a processor that can operate at a faster clock.
This helps both response time and throughput.
But with the end of Moore's law and denied scaling, this has gotten harder.
For this reason, the multi-core era took over.
With additional cores on a processor, one can get more instructions executed per clock,
and this may help response time if queuing is reduced.
In this class, we're going to focus on processor time, which is time spent running a program.
Now let's start comparing performance between machines.
We can basically say machine A is N times faster than machine B,
if execution time of B divided by execution time of A is N.
N is referred to as the speed-up relative to machine B in this case.
We can also specify relative performance differences in terms of percent.
If it takes 15 seconds to run on machine A and 10 seconds on machine B,
then B is 1.5 times faster or 50% faster than B.
Let's go for a deeper understanding of performance.
A processor doesn't know when a program starts or ends.
It only fetches and executes instructions one at a time.
However, processors have different stages or cycles that typically take one machine cycle to execute.
As a quick example, an older Snapdragon from Qualcomm runs at 1 GHz,
which is 1,000 million cycles per second, so the cycle time is 1 nanosecond.
In contrast, the latest AMD Ryzen Zen 5 runs at 4.4 GHz or 4.4 billion cycles per second,
so the cycle time is 0.227 nanoseconds.
All of these metrics are put together to define the iron law of processor performance.
The time to execute program can be broken up into three components.
The first is the number of instructions in the program.
This is the code size or dynamic instruction count,
which heavily depends on the simplicity or complexity of the ISA
as well as the ability of the compiler to optimize for the architecture.
The second term is the cycles per instruction or CPI.
This is purely a function of the implementation,
and it's where a computer architect can make trade-offs in the design
and in how the processor's pieces are built.
This will determine whether instructions will execute in a single cycle,
a few cycles, or many cycles.
The final component is the time per cycle,
which is the time elapsed during one clock cycle.
This is going to be dependent on the designer
and could be different if the same ISA is going to target different markets
with unique implementations of silicon.
All three of these components can be intertwined.
For example, an ISA with very complex instructions
may be hard for the designer to execute in fewer cycles.
There is just too much work to do and not enough time within a cycle to do it.
Let's go over an example utilizing the iron law.
Machine A has a one nanosecond clock period and achieves a CPI of 2.0,
while Machine B has a two nanosecond clock period and achieves a CPI of 1.2,
which is faster and by how much.
Since they're both running the same program,
we can assume that the total number of instructions executed, N, is unchanged.
Taking the product of the CPI and clock period and comparing the two machines,
we find that A is 20% faster than B.
But what if you have a set of programs you wish to use as benchmarks
and want to compare them across multiple machines?
The easiest way to reason about this would be to assume each program is run once
and sum the execution times on each machine.
In this example, Machine B is 9.1 times faster than Machine A.
A second approach is to take the arithmetic mean, which actually is the same results.
In a similar way, it assumes that each program are equally run on a machine,
yielding 9.1x speedup for Machine B.
If the programs are not run equally, then you'll need to take the weighted arithmetic mean
to properly account for how often each program will be run.
Dealing with ratios, as we'll see, is different.
Let's try to use arithmetic mean for ratios and see why it does not work.
The top table shows our runtimes.
The bottom table normalizes them to Machine A.
If we take the arithmetic mean, we'll see that Machine B is 5.05 times slower.
Now let's normalize to Machine B and take the arithmetic mean.
Now we find that Machine A is 5.05 times slower.
How can both machines be 5 times slower than the other?
When finding the mean of ratios, we have to use the geometric mean
because it's independent of which machine is used as the reference.
Now whether or not we normalize to Machine A or to Machine B,
the resulting geometric means or geomens are 1,
which indicate the performance of the two machines are equivalent.
An important point is that the geometric mean of the ratios is not proportional to total runtime.
The arithmetic mean assumes that programs are run an equal number of times,
so in this case, Machine B is faster.
But the geometric mean instead states that both machines are equal
and that would only be true if program 1 is run 100 times more often than program 2.
We need to be aware of the context in which we're comparing performance for multiple programs
to ensure we're comparing apples to apples.
The last topic of this lecture is Amdahl's Law.
This was first presented by Jean Amdahl, a 1952 PhD graduate from the University of Wisconsin-Madison.
It's a simple analytical model that serves to show how important it is to optimize the common case in your system.
Given F, the percent of time a component occupied in your program's runtime,
and S, the speedup you apply to it, then this model estimates the resulting speedup of the entire program.
Let's look at an example.
Your boss challenges you to improve the performance of the next generation processor
by either 1 improving the ALU by 10% or 2 improving the memory pipeline by 10 times.
Since a crucial program is compute intensive,
it spends 95% of the time crunching numbers and 5% of the time waiting for data to transfer via the memory pipeline.
Amdahl's Law can help us compare the two options, and it looks like ALU speedup wins despite a modest 10% speedup.
Speeding up the memory pipeline 10x didn't have much of an effect.
Even though more than 10x may be theoretically impossible,
how much faster do we have to make it in order to equal the ALU speedup?
Theoretically, let's consider an infinite speedup of the memory pipeline.
All requests now take 0 nanoseconds.
Amdahl's Law politely reminds us that this crazy optimization barely moves the result.
Hyper-optimizing a small, uncommon portion of the program execution is very limiting in the overall benchmark.
Working on the common case will always be more important.